Guide to the Gus Mager Papers and Collection of Original Cartoon Art, 1916-1954 SPEC.CGA.MAG
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
Gus Mager Papers and Collection of Original Cartoon Art
1916-1954
SPEC.CGA.MAG
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
1.2 Cubic feet 2 boxes
The Gus Mager Papers and Collection of Original Cartoon Art contains proofs, sketch and composition books, photographs of cartoonist, Charles Augustus "Gus" Mager. Original cartoon art by Gus Mager has been separated and is available in the Original Art Database.
2 boxes: (1) 5" hollinger legal document box (1) 25.25" x 19" x 2.5" flat box
Mager, Gus
Arrangement of Materials
This small collection is arranged by size of materials.
Acquisitions Information
CGA.2017.075: Judith Mager Jim, 2017
Access to Materials
Materials in this collection are available for use, but may be used in the Billy Ireland Cartoon Library & Museum] reading room only. Audio/visual materials and computer media may need a use copy produced before access is allowed. To request material from this finding aid please contact the reading room by email cartoons@osu.edu or by phone 614-292-0538.
Biographical Note
Charles Augustus "Gus" Mager was born in New Jersey in 1878. Here is known mainly for the his Sunday newspaper comic strip "Hawkshaw the Detective," which was a spoof of Sherlock Holmes. "Hawkshaw" ran intermittingly from 1913 to 1922 and from 1931 to 1947. During the 1920s, Mager worked as an assistant on Rudolph Dirks' comic strip "Captain and the Kids." Other comic strips include "Jungle Society" (1904-1906), "Mager's Monks" (1904-1913), "Sherlocko and Watso" (1910-1913; an earlier parody of Sherlock Holmes), "Milliobucks" (1913), "Main Street" (1922-1923), and various other titles.
Mager was also an accomplished painter, whose work was widely exhibited. His paintings are in the collections of the Whitney Museum and the Newark Museum of Art.
Mager died in Pennsylvania in 1956 at the age of 77.
Scope and Contents
This small collection includes proofs of "Sherlocko," "Captain and the Kids," "Hawkshaw the Detective," and "Main Street." In addition to sketch and composition books by Mager, photographs, and copies of the magazine "Outdoor Life" in which Mager wrote and illustrated the column "Game Gimmicks."
Original art by Gus Mager has been separated and cataloged in the Original Art Database.
Related Materials
Works by Gus Miscellaneous clippings about Mager may be found in the library's biography file under his last name.
Separated Materials
Original art has been separated and cataloged in the Original Art Database. The art can be accessed through searching Mager, Gus, 1878-1956
Comic books, strips, etc; Comic strips
- "Sherlocko" proofs, 1924-1925 (Box MAG 1, Folder 1)
- "The Captain and the Kids" and "Hawkshaw the Detective" proofs, 1944-1946 (Box MAG 1, Folder 2)
- "Main Street" proof, 1924 (Box MAG 1, Folder 3)
- Composition Book, "Outdoor Life", 1954-1956 (Box MAG 2, Folder 1)
- Compositions, October-May, undated (Box MAG 2, Folder 2)
- Paramount Composition Book, 1934-1938 (Box MAG 2, Folder 3)
- Photograph of Gus Mager in group, undated (Box MAG 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Gus Mager and Family, 1900-1954 (Box MAG 2, Folder 5)
  Scope and Contents
  1. A young Gus Mager, circa 1900 2. Gus Mager, the Artist. Terrace Street, Newark, NJ, circa 1912 3. Gus Mager the Cartoonist 4. Gus Mager, Matilda Mager, Rudolph Dirks, Helen Dirks, Bob Mager, circa 1908 5. Group Photo: Gus Mager with banjo, Walk Kuhn with Guitar, unknown female and male, James Gress, and "Pop" Hart 6. Gus Mager backpacking in Adirondacks 7. Gus Mager, circa 1954
- Outdoor Life, "Game Gimmicks", April 1953 (Box MAG 2, Folder 6)
- Outdoor Life, "Game Gimmicks", March 1954 (Box MAG 2, Folder 7)
- Outdoor Life, "Game Gimmicks", April 1954 (Box MAG 2, Folder 8)
- "Adventures of Hawkshaw" booklet, 1927 (Box MAG 2, Folder 9)